<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-18T13:02:13+00:00</updated><id>https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/feed.xml</id><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Mathematical generation of normal data for evaluating myocardial perfusion studies</title><link href="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/dbase_normalize/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mathematical generation of normal data for evaluating myocardial perfusion studies"/><published>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/dbase_normalize</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/dbase_normalize/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="topic">Topic</h2> <p>Single-Photon Emission Computed Tomography (SPECT) protocols for left ventricular assessment play a crucial role in detecting ischemia in high-risk patients. To quantitatively evaluate myocardial function, clinicians rely on commercially available solutions for segmenting and reorienting the left ventricle (LV). These solutions are developed using extensive normal datasets, however this approach is having many drawbacks</p> <ul> <li>Whenever a new aperture is being developed a new normal database has to be created to get good quantitative evaluations</li> <li>Normal database establishment carries a high cost and time consuming slowing down the development iteration time of collimators</li> <li>Clinics often screen patients with suspectible cardiac deficiency and rarely healthy individuals, making the creation of normal databases extra work</li> <li>The size of these datasets are fixed and normalized, which might leave out important samples from the distribution</li> </ul> <p>One idea of Kari and Partos to create normal datasets based on badly conditioned cardiac data using only the “normal” subsets of these samples. A mathematical method was developed that synthesizes normal data sets for quantification of regional myocardium perfusion. In clinical practice, regional myocardial perfusion is often measured with a gamma camera and quantified via circumferential profile analysis. Normal reference profile data is used to increase the accuracy of the clinical interpretations. The goal here is to create reference data from an existing set of archived studies. An iterative mathematical method, based on two statistical hypotheses, was used to generate the study set instead of collecting normal examinations from a healthy population.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="task">Task</h2> <p>Develop a method based on [1], [2] which can generate normal data from a reference dataset of ill-conditioned patients.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p>[1] <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?arnumber=1175084&amp;casa_token=YDjkMXjuuUgAAAAA:V-1R4nhJLftTOlbcZwyMXq9BCxbanE9vAN7ub3sZUx4yyxrVxyS0tT0SjUxWSkn75PHHSMHNabhVqw">Mathematical generation of normal data for evaluating myocardial perfusion studies</a>, Marianna et. al.</p> <p>[2] Osszehasonlito adatok eloallitasa bull’s-eye kepek ertekelesehez, Mate et. a.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="contact">Contact</h2> <p>szaqaei@inf.elte.hu, kari.bela@semmelweis.hu</p>]]></content><author><name>Adam Istvan Szucs</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Generating normal databases from non-healthy patients]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Motion correction of Multi-pinhole (MPH) projection frames with metamorphosis</title><link href="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/mc_metamorph/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Motion correction of Multi-pinhole (MPH) projection frames with metamorphosis"/><published>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/mc_metamorph</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/mc_metamorph/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="topic">Topic</h2> <p>Various functional imaging cameras are specialized to acquire the biochemical processes in a time and space-dependent way of different organs in-vivo. The main properties of functional imaging are relatively low resolution and high sensitivity to be manifested in multiple collimation and detection strategies. As a result, the projection geometry in each multi-vendor camera has large variability, making the inherent and acquired imaging artifacts hard to handle by algorithms.</p> <p>We seek a method, which overcomes one of the biggest effects of acquired imperfection, the patient’s motion which interferes with the heart’s motion. It is well known that, the different motion influences may alter the crucial quantitative measures. These are rendered as the main important issues of functional imaging. Solutions exist by multiple commercial approaches already, but only for specific collimation geometries. This motivation inspired the development of an automatic optimization method to overcome the above-mentioned motion artifact with general collimation geometry on the complete detector field-of-view (FOV).</p> <p>The theory (geo mc) is based on a metamorphic control problem with Optimal Transport (OT) augmentation to overcome the problems introduced by the acquired artifacts and intrinsic imaging system. The algorithm is designed on multi-pinhole (MPH) and low energy high resolution (LEHR) collimation with promising a great improvement over Optial Flow (OF) methods. The aim is to further lower the error in total perfusion deficit (TPD) scores for practical ability to apply on the patient Single-Photon Emission Computed Tomography (SPECT) studies as well.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="task">Task</h2> <p>Develop the <a href="https://github.com/JacksonFurrier/ieee_bibm_2024_code">technique</a> further, based on [1], [2] to get better results on MPH apertures with motion phenomena.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p>[1] <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/BIBM62325.2024.10822170">Projection geometry invariant nonrigid motion correction</a>, Adam et. al.</p> <p>[2] <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/GPMC48183.2019.9106957">Automated non-linear motion detection and estimation for MPI SPECT</a>, Adam et. al.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="contact">Contact</h2> <p>szaqaei@inf.elte.hu</p>]]></content><author><name>Adam Istvan Szucs</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Non-linear and projective geometry based motion detection and correction]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Optimization methods in left ventricle segmentation</title><link href="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_lv_optim/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Optimization methods in left ventricle segmentation"/><published>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_lv_optim</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_lv_optim/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="topic">Topic</h2> <p>Image segmentation is a day-to-day task of clinical practitioners to carry out volume/area/surface specific quantities of a region of interest (ROI). In most cases this task can be challenging and too long to solve (multiple hours/half an hour), therefore some level of automation is needed.</p> <p>There are many segmentation methodologies based on different theories, but in most of the cases these are not applied in the practice due to the unacceptable running times. Besides deep-learning the graph-based algorithms are actively being researched and developed. [1] The data being volumetric (3D scalar field) it can be represented as a large graph with nodes being voxels and edges being the connection between neighboring (e.g. 6 neighboring cubes) voxels. With this abstraction, a segmentation task can be thought as a graph partitioning/slicing method to find the desired ROI (e.g. a liver in a CT dataset, thyroids in a SPECT dataset).</p> <p>The graph-based algorithms are often developed in hand with variational image segmentation methods to define an energy which can be minimized on the graph. Sometimes this approach can lead to long running times and complicated optimization tactics. A different approach was introduced in [2] to overcome the drawbacks of the latter. The method is fast and accurate in the segmentation task with a simple isoperimetric cost function. Even though it is fast and accurate solving the isoperimetric problem for instance in most cases this wont suffice (e.g.: full body bone segmentation)</p> <p>Problem with graph-based methods is metrication bias, which renders as low resolution or high computation times. To overcome the aforementioned problem, a continuous optimization [3, 4] can be applied to handle the discrete resolution of graph-based methods. The continuous max-flow (CMF) method is very accurate in classification problems.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="task">Task</h2> <p>Investigate and develop a technique based-on CMF method with shape priors to handle the “few-shot” learning with classical methods. Compare the current method to the competing ones (given by the topic supervisor). Investigate shape descriptors in a statistical setting and compare it to self-supervised methods.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p>[1] <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?arnumber=1580491&amp;casa_token=HD-uw-azqYMAAAAA:cH4e-44fUMcIBPhLoWQNS3LhmNm9Jwyt0QZNWtaQtyecIxaO_Z7ql3jxohmFVrX7KWK34Ca8Dy8OwQ&amp;tag=1">Isoperimetric Graph Partitioning for Image Segmentation</a>, Leo Grady, Eric L. Schwartz</p> <p>[2] <a href="http://leogrady.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/grady2006fast.pdf">Fast, Quality, Segmentation of Large Volumes Isoperimetric Distance Trees</a>, Leo Grady</p> <p>[3] <a href="https://bora.uib.no/bora-xmlui/bitstream/handle/1956/5020/A%20study%20on%20continuous%20max-flow%20and%20min-cut%20approaches.pdf?sequence=1">A study on Continuous Max-flow and Min-cut approaches</a>, Jing Yuan et al.</p> <p>[4] <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2004.11227">Efficient ADMM and Splitting Methods for Continuous Min-cut and Max-flow Problems</a>, Hongpent et al.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="contact">Contact</h2> <p>szaqaei@inf.elte.hu</p>]]></content><author><name>Adam Istvan Szucs</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Classical optimization methods in left ventricle segmentation]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MPI SPECT left ventricle modelling with flow-matching</title><link href="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_shape_modelling_fm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MPI SPECT left ventricle modelling with flow-matching"/><published>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_shape_modelling_fm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_shape_modelling_fm/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="topic">Topic</h2> <p>Single-Photon Emission Computed Tomography (SPECT) left ventricular assessment protocols are important for detecting ischemia in high-risk patients. To quantitatively measure myocardial function, clinicians depend on commercially available solutions to segment and reorient the left ventricle (LV) for evaluation. Based on large normal datasets, the segmentation performance and the high price of these solutions can hinder the availability of reliable and precise localization of the LV delineation. To overcome the aforementioned shortcomings this project aims to give a recipe for diagnostic centers as well as for clinics to automatically segment the myocardium based on small and low-quality labels on reconstructed SPECT, complete field-of-view (FOV) volumes.</p> <p>The way this approach works as compared to the <a href="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_ssl_fs_vit/">self-supervised learning approach</a> is that we first try to understand the shape of the left ventricle during the myocardial perfusin imaging (MPI) SPECT protocol. As in [1] we built a feature space, based on the kernel embedding in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reproducing_kernel_Hilbert_space">reproducing kernel Hilbert space (RKHS)</a>. Constructing the space we assumed a simplistic model, which was a square root function rotated around the x-axis giving us the 3 dimensional surface of the left ventricle. The base model was as simple as it could be, having only hyperparameters controlling the septal, endo and epicardial surfaces of the mycoardial volume. After constructing the distribution of our left ventricular shapes we embedded them with the Wasserstein-2 kernel (Sinkhorn-divergence based one) [4] in the higher dimensional RKHS. During the running of the segmentation we connected the original and the latent space with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahalanobis_distance">Mahalanobis-type distance</a> to sample the feature space during segmentation, ultimately convering the problem into a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Density_estimation">density estimation problem</a>. The basic building blocks were following the footsteps of [2], [3], [5], [6]. Now as per the results, the shape prior was able to describe a well diversified 80 patient dataset, however we would like to push this further and see if we can understand the manifold of distribution of the left ventricular shapes.</p> <p>To overcome the limit in expressability of RKHS-es we plan to investigate <a href="https://mlg.eng.cam.ac.uk/blog/2024/01/20/flow-matching.html">flow matching</a> to get a better insight into the left ventricular shape distribution.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="task">Task</h2> <p>Develop a flow matching based solution to describe the shapes of the left ventricles more accurately. Compare the method to the RKHS based solution and prove enhancement.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p>[1] Myocardial perfusion imaging SPECT left ventricle segmentation with graphs, Adam et. al.</p> <p>[2] <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0031320303000566?casa_token=_OYwvXehkoIAAAAA:90b5a76xe47mkEWeIDckKGlsB6y5NwFX7SHFfinKNxNdXf7C1YvlyfkKJzhB_5gr0ZGKgWPWnKE">Shape statistics in kernel space for variational image segmentation</a>, Daniel et. al.</p> <p>[3] <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-1-4471-1599-1_18">Kernel pca Pattern Reconstruction via Approximate Pre-Images</a>, Bernhard et. al.</p> <p>[4] <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?arnumber=9207630&amp;casa_token=qLFvaMf3MTUAAAAA:NTFR70AIIl5NA3BhQTkIJcA5mQ_Y4x1LTaK-9s1d_qI4VHjQK6jNWAyPcaTcjga-LguyH2BoQ-K_Gw">Wasserstein exponential kernels</a>, Henri et. al.</p> <p>[5] <a href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1023/A:1020826424915.pdf">Diffusion Snakes: Introducing Statistical Shape Knowledge into the Mumford-Shah Functional</a>, Daniel et. al.</p> <p>[6] <a href="https://ipa.iwr.uni-heidelberg.de/ipabib/Papers/Cremers_Kohlberger_Schnoerr:Nonlinear_Shape_Statistics_in_Mumford-Shah_Based_Segmentation.pdf">Nonlinear Shape Statistics in Mumford–Shah Based Segmentation</a>, Daniel et. al.</p> <p>[7] <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02747">Flow Matching for Generative Modeling</a>, Yaron et. al.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="contact">Contact</h2> <p>szaqaei@inf.elte.hu</p>]]></content><author><name>Adam Istvan Szucs</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Shape manifold representation learning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Self-supervised few-shot learning in left ventricle segmentation</title><link href="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_ssl_fs_vit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-supervised few-shot learning in left ventricle segmentation"/><published>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_ssl_fs_vit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jacksonfurrier.github.io/blog/2025/seg_ssl_fs_vit/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="topic">Topic</h2> <p>Single-Photon Emission Computed Tomography (SPECT) left ventricular assessment protocols are important for detecting ischemia in high-risk patients. To quantitatively measure myocardial function, clinicians depend on commercially available solutions to segment and reorient the left ventricle (LV) for evaluation. Based on large normal datasets, the segmentation performance and the high price of these solutions can hinder the availability of reliable and precise localization of the LV delineation. To overcome the aforementioned shortcomings this project aims to give a recipe for diagnostic centers as well as for clinics to automatically segment the myocardium based on small and low-quality labels on reconstructed SPECT, complete field-of-view (FOV) volumes.</p> <p>A self-supervised learning (SSL) approach was developed in [1] with convolutional neural networks (CNN). The technique was based on jigsaw puzzle as a pretext task and supervision on 5 patients as fine-tuning. The method reached good performance on various metrics, however on hypoperfused myocardia it wasn’t able to get acceptable results. A way to enhance the technique is to apply methods from Vision transformers (ViT) on some parts of the architecture and training as well [2], [3]. Furthermore the incorporation of shape information about left ventricles can raise the performance of such methods.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="task">Task</h2> <p>Develop a ViT-based SSL few-shot learning method and investigate the incorporation of shape information in the optimization process.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p>[1] <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/pdf/10.1145/3632047.3632078">Self-supervised segmentation of myocardial perfusion imaging SPECT left ventricles</a>, Adam et al.</p> <p>[2] <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0010482523004195?casa_token=T2dI_3cEndIAAAAA:kPV9wHN_07raKCy6hzW_5CJfFA0AjxmV9yXDoZg6o8l2Z7dKvwGKFE27_pJRpPov6sG2tjsAE-c">A new method incorporating deep learning with shape priors for left ventricular segmentation in myocardial perfusion SPECT images</a>, Fubau et al.</p> <p>[3] <a href="https://openaccess.thecvf.com/content/WACV2022/papers/Hatamizadeh_UNETR_Transformers_for_3D_Medical_Image_Segmentation_WACV_2022_paper.pdf">UNETR: Transformers for 3D Medical Image Segmentation</a></p> <hr/> <h2 id="contact">Contact</h2> <p>szaqaei@inf.elte.hu</p>]]></content><author><name>Adam Istvan Szucs</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Problems with low labeled left ventricle segmentation in MPI SPECT]]></summary></entry></feed>